Guide to the Stanford University, President's Office, Medical School Correspondence
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford University, President's Office, Medical School correspondence
1902-1912
SC0520
Stanford University. Office of the President
0.75 Linear feet
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Stanford University President's Office
Information about Access
None.
HISTORICAL NOTE
Cooper Medical College in San Francisco, which had antecedents in other medical schools in existence as early as 1858, was formally established in 1882 under the leadership of Dr. Levi Cooper Lane. With the financial generosity of Dr. Lane, the College was able to add laboratories and a hospital during the next two decades, but it was also becoming apparent that new sources of support would be necessary for its continued success. In 1901 Cooper Medical College and Stanford University began to talk about the possibility of a union. Between 1902 and 1907 the details of the merger were worked on and a final agreement was reached by the University Board of Trustees on January 31, 1908.
The first faculty was appointed in October 1908. Stanford faculty included among them were Arthur William Meyer, John Maxson Stillman, Oliver Peebles Jenkins, Frank Mace MacFarland, William Freeman Snow, George Clinton Price, and Robert Eckles Swain. From the Cooper faculty were the following: Adolph Barkan, Henry Gibbons, Jr., Joseph Oakland Hirschfelder, Stanley Stillman, Emmet Rixford, William Ophüls, and William Fitch Cheney. Ray Layman Wilbur was also appointed to the faculty at this time.
SCOPE AND CONTENT
These records pertain to the merger of Cooper Medical College and Stanford University. They consist largely of correspondence, with a few reports and financial documents. Most of the letters are addressed to David Starr Jordan, although some of the correspondence is that of George A. Clark, the academic secretary of Stanford University. In addition to the details of the merger, the letters address curriculum issues, faculty appointments, fees, facilities, financial matters, future needs and plans, the medical school library, the possible association with the University of California, and the Lane Medical Lectures. An index to the correspondents is included in this guide.
These records appear to have been part of the university president's office but were at some time separated from other records and bound together. Three volumes, roughly chronological in arrangement, were removed from the four digit collection. The volumes were disassembled but rehoused in sequential order: folders 1 through 14 in box 1 represent the first volume and folders 15 through 23 represent the second volume. Box 2 represents the third volume. Within these three segments, the chronological arrangement of the letters was corrected where necessary.
Access Terms
Barkan, Adolph.; Blake, Clarence J., (Clarence John), -1919; Clark, George A. (George Archibald), 1865-1918.; Cooper Medical College.; Gibbons, Henry, 1840-1911.; Hopkins, Timothy, 1859-1937.; Jordan, David Starr, 1851-1931; Meyer, Arthur William, 1873-; Ophüls, William,, 1871-1933.; Pritchett, Henry S., (Henry Smith), 1857-1939.; Ricketts, Howard Taylor,, 1871-1910.; Rixford, Emmet,, 1865-1938.; Stanford University. School of Medicine.; Stillman, John Maxson, 1852-1923.; Wilbur, Ray L., (Ray Lyman), 1875-1949; Zinsser, Hans,, 1878-1940.; Medical colleges--California.; Medical education.
Collection Contents
- Correspondence, 1902-1912
  - Blake, Clarence J., letter to Jordan, 17-Sep-02 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, February -May 1906 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, April 1906 -November 1908 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Memorandum as to the proposed union of Cooper Medical College with Stanford, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Board of Trustees, correspondence, June -October 1906 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Stillman, J. M. - correspondence with Board of Trustees, October 1906 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Stillman, J. M. - report of special committee, November 1906 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Statement for President's Report for, 1906/07 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Cooper Medical College - report of personal property, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Board of Trustees, October 25, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, February -August 1910 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, September -December 1910 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, September -October 1909 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, November 1909 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, December 8 -December 14, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, December 15 -December 31, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, January -April 1910 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, May 1910 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, June -July 1910 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, August -October 1910 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence undated (Emerich Rosenberg) (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Summary of Board Actions in 1910 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, January -March 1911 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, April 1911 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, May 1911 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, June 1911 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, July 1911 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, August -September 1911 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, October 1911 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, November -December 1911 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, January -February 1912 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, April 1912 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, May 1912 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, June 1912 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, July 1912 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Budget and Plan for Conduct of Business, 1912-13 (Box 2, Folder 15)
INDEX TO CORRESPONDENTS
Abel, John J. Box 1, Folder 15, 16, 19
Alsberg, Carl L. Box 1 Folder 12, 15, 20
Bain, A. J. Box 1 Folder 19
Barkan, Adolph Box 1 Folder 15
Barkan, Adolph Box 2 Folder 7
Barnes, Jasper C. Box 1 Folder 18
Blaisdell, F. E. Box 2 Folder 6
Blake, Clarence J. Box 1 Folder 1, 2
Branner, John C. Box 1 Folder 21, 22
Branner, John C. Box 2 Folder 8, 9
Bridge, Norman Box 1 Folder 19
Burrage, Severance Box 1 Folder 17, 19
Cheney, William F. Box 1 Folder 18
Clark, George A. Box 2 Folder 2-4, 6-8, 9-12
Coca, Arthur F. Box 1 Folder 12, 16
Comstock, Annie Box 1 Folder 20
Coulter, John M. Box 1 Folder 12
Crawford, Albert C. Box 1 Folder 19, 22
Crothers, George E. Box 1 Folder 5-6, 10-11, 19
Davis, Horace Box 1 Folder 12
Dean, Banford Box 1 Folder 19
Dresbach, Melvin Box 1 Folder 19-20
Ellinwood, C. N. Box 1 Folder 3, 5
Elliott, O. L. Box 2 Folder 8
Flexner Box 1 Folder 15
Gage, Simon H. Box 1 Folder 3, 20
Gay, Frederick P. Box 1 Folder 18
Gibbons, Jr., Henry Box 1 Folder 3, 9, 13, 17
Gilman, Philip K. Box 1 Folder 12, 16
Hall, James P. Box 1 Folder 17
Hatcher, Robert A. Box 1 Folder 19
Hewlett, Albion W. Box 1 Folder 11, 19
Hirschfelder, J. O. Box 1 Folder 3
Hodgson, Caspar W. Box 1 Folder 16, 18
Hollmann, E. F. Box 2 Folder 13-14
Hood, S. B. Box 1 Folder 18
Hopkins, Timothy Box 1 Folder 13-14, 21-22
Hopkins, Timothy Box 2 Folder 4-5
Huey, Edmund B. Box 1 Folder 15
Hunt, Reid Box 1 Folder 12, 20
Hyde, James N. Box 1 Folder 12, 18
Jenkins, O. P. Box 1 Folder 3
Jordan, David S. Box 1 Folder 2, 3, 5, 11-14, 17, 20
Jordan, David S. Box 2 Folder 2-7, 10-11
Judson, Henry Pratt Box 1 Folder 19
Keeble, W. H. Box 1 Folder 18
Kerr, Abram T. Box 1 Folder 19
Little, Hubert Box 2 Folder 7
MacFarland, Frank M. Box 1 Folder 3
Meyer, Arthur W. Box 1 Folder 13, 15, 20-22
Meyer, Arthur W. Box 2 Folder 7-9
Montgomery, Walter A. Box 1 Folder 18
Muirhead, A. L. Box 1 Folder 19
Newman, John G. Box 1 Folder 18
Ophüls, W. Box 1 Folder 2-3, 12-21
Ophüls, W. Box 2 Folder 6, 8, 12-14
Price, George C. Box 1 Folder 3
Pritchett, Henry S. Box 1 Folder 22
Pritchett, Henry S. Box 2 Folder 4-5
Richards, A. N. Box 1 Folder 17, 19
Ricketts, Howard T. Box 1 Folder 12, 17-19
Ritchie, John W. Box 1 Folder 12, 16-18
Rixford, Emmet Box 1 Folder 11, 14
Rixford, Emmet Box 2 Folder 4
Rosenberg, Emerich Box 1 Folder 23
Sedgarck, W. T. Box 1 Folder 16
Sloss, Leon Box 1 Folder 12
Smith, Theobald Box 1 Folder 15
Snow, William F. Box 1 Folder 3, 16
Spalding, Alfred B. Box 1 Folder 21
Stillman, J. M. Box 1 Folder 2, 6-7, 11-14, 17, 20-22
Stillman, Stanley Box 1 Folder 13
Swain, R. E. Box 1 Folder 3
Voegtlin, C. Box 1 Folder 12, 15, 20
Walker, Ernest L. Box 1 Folder 16
Welch, William H. Box 2 Folder 6
Wheeler, Benjamin Box 1 Folder 3
Wilbur, Ray Lyman Box 1 Folder 2, 14-16, 19
Wilbur, Ray Lyman Box 2 Folder 2-14
William, Tom A. Box 1 Folder 13
Wilson & Wilson, attorneys Box 1 Folder 21
Zinsser, Hans Box 1 Folder 12, 13, 19, 22
Zinsser, Hans Box 2 Folder 4